A Guide to the Douglass Family Collection, 1887-1945
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Douglass Family Collection 1887-1945
Thomas Balch Library
M 103, VC 0065
This collection is generally grouped into three parts: Martha Strother's papers, the Love family papers, and James Edwards Douglass's papers. It contains letters and postcards, military papers and pamphlets, and photographs. This collection is arranged chronologically by recipient. The accompanying visual collection designation describes where each visual item is located in the collection.
Brenda Douglass, Purcellville, VA. Sara Love Douglass, Aldie, VA
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Brenda Douglass, Purcellville, VA. Sara Love Douglass, Aldie, VA
Alternative Form Available
None.
Accruals
2008.0067, 2009.0078
Biographical Information
The Douglass, Strother, and Love families, related by marriage, lived in Loudoun and Fauquier counties.
Martha Strother (17 January 1892-13 November 1969), the daughter of William H. Strother (1849-1894) and Nancy D. Anderson (1864-1898), was born in Fauquier County, VA, and raised by her maternal grandmother Martha A. Roberts Anderson (20 November 1835-9 July 1911) following the death of her parents. On 14 November 1917, she married John Moore Douglass (30 November 1888-14 January 1947), with whom she had three children: John Moore (b. 1918), James Edwards (Ned) (15 June 1920-29 January 1985), and Martha Anne (b. 1930). John Moore Douglass owned and operated Aldie Mill, a historically significant Loudoun County mill now owned by the state of Virginia operating from 1807-1971, until his death in 1947. Martha Strother Douglass was a member of the Aldie Presbyterian Church and the Aldie Horticultural Society until 1948 when she moved to Chevy Chase, MD. Before her death in 1969, she moved back to Aldie, VA.
George S. Cable (22 July 1858-26 June 1928) was a merchant in Fauquier Country. He married Lula H. Anderson (4 September 1869-4 March 1888) on 8 September 1886, and was Martha Strother's uncle by marriage. He had one child, Lula Anderson Cable (2 March 1888-19 September 1894) who died at the age of 7. Following the death of his wife and his daughter, George Cable married Catherine Rogers Green, known as "Katie," (12 August 1870-4 October 1932), on 20 June 1895, with whom he had three children.
Catharine E. Strother (1892-1940), known as "Kate," was the daughter of George Thomas Strother (1855-1923) and Lou Bayly (1866-1944). She was a paternal first cousin to Martha Strother.
William Smith Strother (21 May 1882-19 September 1972) was the son of James Lewis Strother (1850-1916) and Mary Elizabeth Smith (1849-1917). On 8 January 1919, he married Louis Henrietta Delaplane (26 June 1889-8 February 1984) and had two children. Originally a farmer in Fauquier County, he later taught at the Millard Prep School in Washington D.C. He was a paternal first cousin to Martha Strother.
The Fenton Mercer Love family lived in Jefferson, Loudoun County in the late 1800s and early 1900s. Fenton Mercer Love (9 June 1853-13 May 1935) was a farmer. He and his wife, Gertrude Temple Woolf Love (15 April 1853-24 May 1934), had five sons. Andrew Morris Love (August 1883-1 June 1943) was a farmer, and married Ruth H. Grubb (December 1885-1 June 1943), with whom he had two children, Sara (b. 28 May 1919) and James (1921-1 June 1943). On 1 June 1943, Thomas William Clatterbuck (10 April 1910-16 June 1944) murdered Andrew Morris Love, his wife, and his son in a debt dispute. Ernest Temple Love (24 May 1885-13 March 1966) moved to New York City and then to Albuquerque, New Mexico, where he married, had one son, and became a successful banker. Fenton Mercer Love (February 1887-16 August 1964) married and became a farmer, joining the Lovettsville Farmers Club. James Woolf Love (1 Nov 1889-27 May 1924) was a soldier in World War I, stationed in France. Oscar M. Love (2 May 1892-5 January 1977) moved to Albuquerque, New Mexico and became a banker, marrying and having five children.
James Edwards Douglass (15 June 1920-29 January 1985) was a son of John Moore Douglass and Martha Strother Douglass, and worked at Aldie Mill until World War II started. Joining the army on 14 May 1942, he was a bomber pilot in Italy and attained the rank of sergeant. He flew twenty-one missions before he was wounded in the left eye on 16 November 1944. After several months of treatment, both on the warfront and the home front, he was released from the Valley Forge General Hospital in Pennsylvania. In 1945, he separated from the military after 3 years, 4 months of service. He owned and operated Aldie Mill until it closed in 1971.
Scope and Content
This collection is generally grouped into three parts: Martha Strother’s papers, the Love family papers, and James Edwards Douglass’s papers. It contains letters and postcards, military papers and pamphlets, and photographs. This collection is arranged chronologically by recipient. The accompanying visual collection designation describes where each visual item is located in the collection.
The first part of the collection contains handwritten letters and postcards received by Martha Strother primarily from 1911-1913 when she was in her early twenties, although there are four earlier letters in the collection dating from 1906 to 1910. The letters were written to Martha Strother from a wide circle of acquaintances and family members, covering a variety of topics from recent news and visiting invitations to thank you notes and declarations of love.
Besides letters and postcards, the collection contains two small, undated, unidentified photographs and some handwritten copies of popular songs and poetry from the early 1900s.
There is one undated note, and one Christmas postcard from 1910 to Mrs. Anderson, who presumably is Martha's grandmother.
There is one letter to George S. Cable dated 7 September 1887 from H. M. Kingsley, owner of the Kingsley Brothers Loudoun Valley Creamery in Hamilton, VA, saying Burr Hamilton (9 July 1828-6 September 1895) could make a mill more profitable.
There are two postcards to Catharine E. Strother, dated 1911 and 23 January 1913. The 1911 postcard wishes her a Merry Christmas, and the 1913 postcard asks her to pick the sender up from the train station.
There is one postcard to William Smith Strother dated 7 September 1911 from Nancy.
The second part of the collection contains handwritten letters and postcards from Ernest and James Love to their parents Fenton and Gertrude Love, as well as assorted letters from friends and family. James wrote all his letters to his parents and younger brother Oscar telling them about army life when he was fighting in World War I, and sent home picture postcards of France. Additionally, there are six government-issued World War II ration books from 1942 used by Andrew Morris Love and his family, one letter from Sara Love to her parents, and a copy of one letter to John Moore Douglass from his brother James Edwards.
The third part of the collection contains handwritten and typed letters mailed in 1945 to James Edwards Douglass from army friends while he was in recovery. In this group there are also some blotters from the 1940s with pictures of women painted on them. Additionally, there are many government documents regarding the release of soldiers from the army, including information booklets with instructions for re-integrating into civilian life and some forms for filing a claim with the National Service Life Insurance. This group contains three pictures taken while James Edwards Douglass was in Italy, one of which is a picture of him and his army friends.
Arrangement
Chronological
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Ancestry Library, www.ancestrylibrary.com, accessed 16 July 2014.
Baird, Nancy, Carol Jordan, and Joseph Scherer. Fauquier County [Virginia]: Tomb Inscriptions, volumes 1 & 2. Westminster, MD. Heritage Books, Inc, 2000.
Douglass Family Collection (M 103), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Duncan, Patricia B. Fauquier County, Virginia: Marriage Register 1883-1906. Westminster, MD. Heritage Records, 2008.
Fishback, Mary. Interview with Sara Love Douglass, 14 July 2014.
Loudoun County Virginia Military Separation Notices, 1918-1995 (M 004), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Loudoun Restoration and Preservation Society, 1968-2009, (M 094), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Northern Virginia Regional Park Authority: Aldie Mill Historic Park, http://www.nvrpa.org/park/aldie_mill_historic_park, accessed 8 July 2014.
Obituary, Loudoun-Times Mirror, 20 August 1964.
Obituary, Loudoun-Times Mirror, 2 June 1966.
Obituary, Loudoun Times-Mirror, 20 November 1969.
Obituary, Loudoun-Times Mirror, 20 January 1977.
Scheel, Eugene M. Loudoun Discovered: Communities, Corners, and Crossroads, volume four. Leesburg, VA. The Friends of the Thomas Balch Library, 2002.
Swartwout, Ashley. Interview with Brenda Douglass, 14 July 2014.
Virginia Outdoors Foundation. Aldie Mills. Richmond VA. Virginia Outdoors Foundation, 1983.
www.findagrave.com, accessed 21 July 2014.
Other Finding Aid
Past Perfect Catalogue records
Technical Requirements
None
Related Material
Aldie Horticultural Society Records (M 009), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA; Loudoun County Virginia Military Separation Notices, 1918-1995 (M 004), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA; Virginia Outdoors Foundation. Aldie Mills. Richmond, VA. Virginia Outdoors Foundation, 1983.
Contents List
  - Martha Strother's papers
    - Correspondence: Martha Strother, 1906-1910
    - Correspondence: Martha Strother, January-August 1911
    - Correspondence: Martha Strother, September-December 1911
    - Correspondence: Martha Strother, January-May 1912
    - Correspondence: Martha Strother, July-August 1912
    - Correspondence: Martha Strother,reconstructed letter, July 1912
    - Correspondence: Martha Strother, September-October 1912
    - Correspondence: Martha Strother, November-December 1912
    - Correspondence: Martha Strother, January 1913
    - Correspondence: Martha Strother, February 1913
    - Correspondence: Martha Strother, March-July 1913
    - Correspondence: Martha Strother, August-September 1913
    - Correspondence: Martha Strother, October-November 1913
  - Martha Strother's papers
    - Correspondence: Martha Strother, December 1913
    - Correspondence: Martha Strother, 1916
    - Correspondence: Martha Strother, no date
    - Unused picture postcards
    - Empty Envelopes, 1911-1913
    - Murphy Opera House program, 1913
    - Photographs, Martha Srother
    - Poetry
    - Textiles found in collection: tatting and burlap
    - Correspondence: Mrs. Anderson, 1910
    - Correspondence: George S. Cable, 1887
    - Correspondence: Catharine E. Strother, 1911-1913
    - Correspondence: William Smith Strother 1911
  - The Love family's papers
    - Advertisement blotter of Millner and Speer, Purcellville, VA, circa 1916-1922
    - Army Promotion, 1918
    - Calling card of Oscar Love, envelope addressed to James W. Love, and letterhead of YMCA, Washington D.C.
    - A Catechism for Infant Classes by W. G. E. Cunnyngham, D.D. Nashville, Tenn. Publishing House Methodist Episcopal Church, South. Smith & Lamar, Agents, 1913
    - Correspondence: Gertrude Love, 1917-1919
    - Correspondence: Ernest Love, 1919
    - Correspondence: James Love, February-July 1918
    - Correspondence: James Love, August 1918-April 1919
    - Correspondence: Sara Love, 1938
    - Ration Books, 1942
    - John Moore Douglass, 1943
    - Textiles found in collection: green and red ribbon
  - James Edwards Douglass's papers
    - Army stationary
    - World War II blotters with images
    - Correspondence: James Edwards Douglass, 1945
    - Empty envelope addressed to T/Sgt James Edwards Douglass, 1945
    - Instructions for Army discharge
    - National Service Life Insurance forms, 1945
    - Pamphlets for returning soldiers, 1944-1945
    - Photographs: James Edwards Douglass
- VC 0065
  - Wishes you a merry Christmas, (Box 1, Folder 1), 1906
  - Warren Green Hotel, Warrenton, Va. (Box 1, Folder 2) 1915 ca
  - Warren Green Hotel, Warrenton, Va. (Box 1, Folder 2) 1915 ca
  - To wish you a happy New Year (Box 1, Folder 2) 1911
  - The Bridge at Gwynn Oak Park, Baltimore, Md. (Box 1, Folder 2) 1911
  - Looking Up the Pike -- Purcellville, Va. (Box 1, Folder 2) 1911
  - Steamer Louise leaving Baltimore for Tolchester Beach, Md., (Box 1, Folder 2), 1911
  - If my face was my fortune I couldn't send you this card, (Box 1, Folder 2), 1911
  - Residence H. Y. Robinson, Huntsville, Tex., (Box 1, Folder 2), 1911
  - We're afraid to go home in the dark, (Box 1, Folder 2), 1909
  - Asheville, N.C., Riverside Lake, (Box 1, Folder 2), 1911
  - I'm kneeling to you, appealing to you; For I have a tender feeling for you., 1911
  - The Falls, Great Falls, Va., near Washington, D. C., (Box 1, Folder 2), 1911
  - [A Gray eye is a sly eye...], (Box 1, Folder 3), 1910
  - Sepia Smoke No. 124, (Box 1, Folder 3), 1911
  - State War & Navy Departments, Washington, D. C., (Box 1, Folder 3), 1911
  - Emerald Pool, Yellowstone National Park., (Box 1, Folder 3), 1911
  - To wish you Christmas Blessings., (Box 1, Folder 3), 1911
  - Waiting for a certain girl, (Box 1, Folder 3), 1912
  - Wishing you lots of Christmas fun., (Box 1, Folder 3), 1911
  - Thanksgiving Day, (Box 1, Folder 3), 1911
  - Banking Room, Shenandoah Valley National Bank, Winchester, Va.,(Box 1, Folder 3), 1911
  - Tennis Girl, (Box 1, Folder 3), 1908
  - Merry Christmas, (Box 1, Folder 3), 1911
  - Christmas Greetings, (Box 1, Folder 3), 1911
  - Best Christmas Wishes, (Box 1, Folder 3), 1911
  - A Merry Christmas, (Box 1, Folder 3), 1911
  - [I wish a merry Christmas to you...], (Box 1, Folder 3), 1911
  - A Merry Christmas, (Box 1, Folder 3), 1911
  - Best Wishes for Christmas, (Box 1, Folder 3), 1911
  - Hoar Frost and Winter Snows (A Merry Christmas), (Box 1, Folder 3), 1911
  - By winding stream., (Box 1, Folder 4), 1912
  - [Girl with roses], (Box 1, Folder 4), 1912
  - The sweetest story ever told., (Box 1, Folder 4), 1912
  - Centenary M. E. Church, South, Cape Girardeau, Mo., (Box 1, Folder 4), 1912
  - U.S. Capitol, Washington, D. C., (Box 1, Folder 5), 1912
  - I likes peaches. 'Specially, w'en dey is girls, (Box 1, Folder 5), 1911
  - Valley of Death and Little Round Top, Gettysburg, Pa., 1912
  - Inlet by moonlight., (Box 1, Folder 5), 1912
  - Horseshoe Cave, Front Royal, Va., (Box 1, Folder 5), 1912
  - Shenandoah River and Bridges, Riverton, Va., (Box 1, Folder 5), 1912
  - Vy hafn't I got a girl, vot?, (Box 1, Folder 5), 1912
  - Morgan's Duck Farm, Largest in the World, Riverton, Va., (Box 1, Folder 5), 1912
  - Battle Street, North from Center St., Manassas, Va., (Box 1, Folder 5), 1912
  - Norfolk and Western R. R. Station, Hagerstown, Md., (Box 1, Folder 7), 1912
  - Morgan's Duck Farm, Largest in the World, Riverton, Va., (Box 1, Folder 7), 1912
  - Mount Vernon, Home of Washington, Mt. Vernon, Va., (Box 1, Folder 7), 1912
  - Front Royal, Va., (Box 1, Folder 7), 1912
  - They keep things to themselves in Front Royal, That's why I linger here, (Box 1, Folder 7), 1912
  - Carnegie Library, Washington, (Box 1, Folder 8), 1912
  - Bureau of Engraving and Printing, Washington, D. C., (Box 1,Folder 8), 1910
  - Wishing you a Merry Christmas, (Box 1, Folder 8), 1912
  - Christmas Greeting, (Box 1, Folder 8), 1912
  - With best New Year Wishes, (Box 1, Folder 8), 1912
  - Shipping cotton, Alabama River, Montgomery, Ala., 1912
  - Pennsylvania's New Capitol, Harrisburg, Pa., (Box 1, Folder 9), 1913
  - Mt. Vernon Mansion, Va., (Box 1, Folder 9), 1913
  - With all kind wishes and Greetings for a Happy New Year, (Box 1, Folder 9), 1913
  - Sepia Wooden Shoe No. 401, (Box 1, Folder 10), 1913
  - I long to be "yours trooly", (Box 1, Folder 10), 1913
  - Sepia Wooden Shoe No. 406, (Box 1, Folder 10), 1913
  - Horseshoe Cave, Front Royal, Va. (Box 1, Folder 10), 1913
  - Greetings on Washington's Birthday., (Box 1, Folder 10), 1913
  - High School Building, Front Royal, Va., (Box 1, Folder 10), 1913
  - St. Patrick's Day Greetings, (Box 1, Folder 11), 1913
  - West Main Street, Front Royal, Va., (Box 1, Folder 11), 1913
  - Wishing you a Happy Easter (Box 1, Folder 11), 1913
  - I bring you Easter Greeting (Box 1, Folder 11) 1913
  - State, War & Navy Departments, Washington, D.C., (Box 1,Folder 11), 1913
  - It is better to love someone you can't have than to have someone you can't love, (Box 1, Folder 11), 1913
  - White House, Washington, D. C., (Box 1, Folder 12), 1913
  - The Crowd that met me at Atlantic City, N. J., (Box 1, Folder 12), 1913
  - East Entrance, White House, Washington, D. C., (Box 1, Folder 12), 1913
  - U. S. Capitol, Washington, D. C., (Box 1, Folder 12), 1913
  - The Reservoir of Luray's Water System, 3 miles east of Luray, Va., (Box 1, Folder 12), 1913
  - [May you welcome Christmas...], (Box 2, Folder 1), 1913
  - With Best Wishes for a Merry Christmas, (Box 2, Folder 1), 1913
  - [Accept, I pray, this Christmas card from me...], (Box 2, Folder 1), 1913
  - Christmas greetings, (Box 2, Folder 1), 1913
  - With Best Wishes for a Merry Christmas, (Box 2, Folder 1), 1913
  - A Merry Christmas, (Box 2, Folder 1), 1913
  - May your best be bettered this Glad New Year., (Box 2, Folder 1), 1913
  - [I wish you for the New Year...], (Box 2, Folder 1), 1913
  - May you have a Happy New Year!, (Box 2, Folder 1), 1913
  - New Year's Greeting, (Box 2, Folder 1), 1913
  - High School, Louisa, Va., (Box 2, Folder 2), 1916
  - Saracen's Tent, Caverns of Luray, Va., (Box 2, Folder 3), 1910 ca
  - A Joyful Christmas, (Box 2, Folder 3), 1910 ca
  - Blessings bright as dew from heaven fall upon you., (Box 2, Folder 3), 1910 ca
  - Easter Greetings, (Box 2, Folder 3), 1917 ca
  - I don't mind bein' roped in by the right gal., (Box 2, Folder 3), 1912
  - Greetings from Markham, Va., (Box 2, Folder 3), 1908
  - May this be a happy New Year., (Box 2, Folder 3), 1910 ca
  - Football squad, Eastern College, Manassas, Va. (Box 2, Folder 3), 1909 ca
  - The likes of U make the whole world glad., (Box 2, Folder 3), 1915 ca
  - [What joy at Christmas time...] (Box 2, Folder 3), 1915 ca
  - Birthday greetings (Box 2, Folder 4), 1915 ca
  - [Will you, won't you, do you, don't you...] 1915 ca
  - Do you know any nice little girl who hasn't any beau? (Box 2, Folder 4), 1911
  - [May you always be in clover...] (Box 2, Folder 4), 1915 ca
  - [Woman in gingham print dress and hat](Box 2, Folder 4), 1910 ca
  - Overpowering beauty (Box 2, Folder 4), 1909
  - Overpowering beauty (Box 2, Folder 4), 1910 ca
  - [North Carolina song] (Box 2, Folder 4), 1909
  - [Woman wearing large hat], (Box 2, Folder 7), 1910 ca
  - [Woman with bow in hair], (Box 2, Folder 7), 1910 ca
  - Merry Christmas, (Box 2, Folder 10), 1910
  - May Christmas Blessings on thee shine, and Joy and Peace be ever thine, (Box 2, Folder 12), 1911
  - [Georgetown University on hill top...], (Box 2, Folder 12), 1913
  - Signs of a thaw, (Box 2, Folder 13), 1910 ca
  - [Advertisement blotter for Millner & Speer, Purcellville, Va.], (Box 2, Folder 14), 1916 ca
  - Best wishes for the New Year, (Box 2, Folder 18), 1917
  - The Kitchen, Paul Revere House, Boston, Mass., (Box 2, Folder 19), 1919
  - Lower New York and Bay, (Box 2, Folder 19), 1919
  - Nice. -- Jardin Albert 1st, (Box 2, Folder 20), 1918
  - Nice. -- Le Quai de Etats-Unis, vue prise des Ponchettes, (Box 2, Folder 20), 1918
  - [Cote d'Or. - Chatilion sur Seine...], (Box 2, Folder 20), 1918
  - Chatillon sur Seine - Rue de Chanmont,(Box 2, Folder 20), 1918
  - Chateau d Ancy-le-Franc (Yonne) -- Chambre de Judith (Box 2, Folder 20), 1918
  - Sainte-Menehould Marne -- Hopital Chanzy, rue Chanzy (Box 2, Folder 20), 1918
  - Nice.-- Le Monastere de Cimiez (Box 2, Folder 21), 1919
  - Nice.-- Cimiez. -- Cour due Monastere. -- Le Puits. (Box 2, Folder 21), 1919
  - Monte-Carlo. -- Dans La Prairie. (Box 2, Folder 21), 1919
  - Toulon. -- Arsenal Maritime. -- Porte Castignan. -- Sorlie des Ouvriers. (Box 2, Folder 21), 1919
  - [Two story house set among trees], (Box 2, Folder 33), 1941
  - [Group of four soldiers in uniform] (Box 2, Folder 33), 1945
  - [Unidentified soldier standing in front of building], (Box 2, Folder 33), 1940s ca
  - [Soldier Bob Parsons standing in front of building] (Box 2, Folder 33), 1940s ca